<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the art of great artillery, viz. The explanation of the most excellent and necessary definitions, and questions, pronounced and propounded, by that rare souldier and mathematician, Thomas Digges Esquire and by him published, in his Stratiaticos, and Pantometria, concerning great ordinance, and his theorems thereupon. Together, vvith certaine expositions, and answers thereunto adioyned: written by Robert Norton gunner. And by him dedicated, to the worshipfull Iohn Reinolds Esquire, master gunner of England.</title>
            <author>Norton, Robert, d. 1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854710</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the art of great artillery, viz. The explanation of the most excellent and necessary definitions, and questions, pronounced and propounded, by that rare souldier and mathematician, Thomas Digges Esquire and by him published, in his Stratiaticos, and Pantometria, concerning great ordinance, and his theorems thereupon. Together, vvith certaine expositions, and answers thereunto adioyned: written by Robert Norton gunner. And by him dedicated, to the worshipfull Iohn Reinolds Esquire, master gunner of England.</title>
                  <author>Norton, Robert, d. 1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Allde, for Iohn Tap, and are to bee sold at his shop, at the corner of Saint Magnus Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Digges, Leonard, d. 1571? --  Stratioticos --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Digges, Leonard, d. 1571? --  Pantometria --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Artillery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20147:1"/>
            <p>OF THE ART OF GREAT ARTILLERY, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi> THE EXPLANATION of the moſt excellent and neceſſary Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, and Queſtions, pronounced and propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by that rare Souldier and Mathematician, <hi>Thomas Digges</hi> Eſquire; and by him publiſhed, in his Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaticos, and Pantometria, concerning great Ordinance, and his Theorems thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together,</hi> VVith certaine Expoſitions, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thereunto adioyned: Written by <hi>Robert Norton</hi> Gunner.</p>
            <p>And by him Dedicated, to the Worſhipfull <hi>Iohn Reinolds</hi> Eſquire, Maſter Gunner of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edw: Allde,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Tap,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop, at the corner of Saint <hi>Magnus Church.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20147:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20147:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Worſhipfull <hi>John Reinolds</hi> Eſquire, Maſter Gunner of England: <hi>Robert Norton</hi> Gunner, wiſheth all health and happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Sir, (as your ſometimes Scholler, &amp; your now ſubſtitute) giue me leaue, to ſhew ſome part of my dutifull thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for your many louing fauours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued; your kinde inſtructions, your free helping hand to the beginning of my encouragement, by your louing Certificate (to the right Honourable the Lord <hi>Carew</hi> Mr. of his Maieſties Ordinance) of my ſufficiency to performe the place and Office of a Gunner, for his Maieſties ſeruice: I therefore haue preſumed to demonſtrate a part of my duty herein, the rather for the louing reſpect you haue euer ſhewed vnto me, and to all others vnder your Commaund, that endeuour to become ſeruiceable for our King, and Countrey, by the diligent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in the excellent Art of great Artillery: It being my chance of late Sir, to turne ouer <hi>Mr. Digges</hi> his Bookes, intituled <hi>Stratiaticos,</hi> and <hi>Pantometria,</hi> to light vpon certaine dificill Definition, obſcure The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orems, and ſome ſubtill queſtions, concerning the
<pb facs="tcp:20147:3"/>
vſe of great Ordinance, which as <hi>Mr. Diggs</hi> there ſaith, though he long ſince publikely propounded them, that none hath yet vndertaken to anſwer any one of them: wherefore in his laſt edition with ſhort Marginall notes, yes and no, himſelfe hath darkly reſolued ſome of them, as hereafter in the Margent appeareth, whereof I haue vndertaken to make a more plaine Expoſition of them &amp; the reſt, aſwell for mine own, as for others furtherance. And wheras he hath there coated certaine publiſhed Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in this Science, I haue thought fit to ioyne them together, with ſome other Errors that I haue alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied in other Authors writing of this Art: All which I haue preſumed to publiſh vnder your iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Patronage, hoping that my willing pains ſhal neither incurre diſgrace, nor diſpleaſe, but rather that theſe my firſt Fruits wil be accepted with ſuch loue as I truly offer them, whereby I ſhall be encouraged (with your good leaue) hereafter to proceed further with my Treatiſe of the Art of Artillery, wherein I perſwade my ſelfe, that the moſt neceſſary particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars belonging to the Gunners Art, are more acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed, then in any other Treatiſe in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage yet extant: And ſo I ſhall endeuour to deſerue the continuance of your loue and fauour, and will reſt at his Lordſhips, and your Worſhips command, both whom, I pray God euer to bleſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Norton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:20147:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O commend the Art and Practice of Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it were vtterly needleſſe, for that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, that all other Sciences are therein v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as in their conuenient and proper Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, and grounded on ſupreme vertue, ſeeing that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it no Kingdome or Common-weale, can either bee or continue in Peace, or defend it ſelfe, nor offend their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; it being the powerfull Regent in our Modern <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia:</hi> for that it deſtroyeth Enemies, depreſſeth Tyrants, chaſteneth Rebels, encreaſeth Dominions, and is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon make-peace, and Conſeruor of tranquillity in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Common-weales. It conſiſteth of many ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Theoricall and Practicall parts, wherein Knowledge muſt be the Pylot of Action, or elſe the action will proue but ſillily ſimple. The Theorick in this (as in all other Sciences) being the fundamentall ground-worke of the practicke part thereof; Therefore Knowing from Doing, muſt be no more ſeperated then Letters from Armes: this made the Hebrew, Egiptian, and Perſian Souldiers, to be aſwell Prieſts as Gentlemen; and the Grecians to be both Philoſophers and Captaines, and the Romaines to be both Souldiers and Schollers; whereby each of them got for their Nation a world of honour. <hi>M. Diggs</hi> ſaid very well, that it fares in this Art, as in Soldiary, and in
<pb facs="tcp:20147:4"/>
Nauigation; for as many a priuate Souldier, whoſe braines will only reach how to ſtand Sentinell, and to March to his Guard, yet takes himſelfe to be a perfect Souldier, but if once his wit bee capable to become <hi>Corporall of the field,</hi> or <hi>Sargeant Maior,</hi> then he comes to ſee his former ignorance and wants. Euen ſo the Common Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, if he can but ſay his Compaſſe, furle a Sayle, and take turne at Helme and Lead, doth leſſe know his ignorance, then ſuch a Maſter or Pilot at hath ſayled a ſhip by his Chart, Compaſſe and Art, round the world; And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in this Art, many ſilly Gunners that neuer ſounded the deepe Channell of this Art, will not ſticke to ſay, they know enough, and ſcorne to learne more, when they God knowes vnderſtand not the first principles of good Art or practiſe; but if by chance, or miſchance, they made a good ſhott once, though without vnderſtanding of the true cauſe of it, it muſt vphold their reputation for euer, and be ſufficient to make Fooles proud. This may chance to be returned me home, yet I care not, for I hope to eſcape the name of a Coward (though my purſe be cudgelled) for that I haue taken vp thoſe weapons, that with a challenge were laid downe ſo long agoe; But let them that are enuious commendor come mend it, and ſo I end.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Theirs that loue Art and Practiſe,</hi> Robert Norton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20147:4"/>
            <head>Certaine Definitions taken out of <hi>Mr. Digges</hi> his Pyrotechnie, and publiſhed in his <hi>Pantometria</hi> concerning Great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. Explaned by <hi>R. N.</hi> Gunner.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. Digges.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR as much as by the hollow</hi> Cylinder <hi>or</hi> Trunke <hi>of the Peece, the violence of all ſhotte of Great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie is not onely directed, but alſo increaſed, I call that hollow</hi> Cylinder <hi>of the Peece, her</hi> Soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. Norton.</speaker>
               <p>This <hi>Soule</hi> is vſually termed by the moſt experienced <hi>Gunners,</hi> the <hi>Concaue Cylinder,</hi> or <hi>Bore</hi> of the <hi>Peece:</hi> And when ſhe is loaded, ſo much thereof as containeth her Charge, is called her <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> or <hi>Charged Cylinder,</hi> whether ſhe be <hi>Equally Bored,</hi> or <hi>Camber Bored;</hi> and the reſt that is vnfilled, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>vacant Cylinder</hi> of her <hi>Bore.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Mettaline ſubſtance of the Peece, of what ſhape, kinde, or proportion ſoeuer, I call</hi> The Body of the Peece.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>The ſeuerall parts of the Mettallyne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of each <hi>Peece,</hi> are diſtinctly knowne to <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> by diuers and ſeuerall <hi>Names:</hi> As the thickeſt of her Mettall at the moſt eminent ring of her
<pb facs="tcp:20147:5"/>
Breech is called her <hi>Baſe-ring</hi> or <hi>Carnooze,</hi> the whole length of her ſhaft, is called her <hi>Chaſe;</hi> and thoſe parts of Mettall that <hi>M. Digges</hi> elſe-where calls her <hi>Eares,</hi> are by <hi>Gunners,</hi> called her <hi>Trunnions;</hi> and before her <hi>Trunnions</hi> that part of her chaſe towards her <hi>Neck</hi> (which is neere the Mouth) is called her <hi>Coronice:</hi> Her formoſt extreme of her Chaſe, is called her Mouth or <hi>Muzle ring, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Soule <hi>in all principall Peeces of Battery is euer a perfect vniforme</hi> Cylinder <hi>comprehended in a Circular Colume, and two equall Circles, whereof the one I call the</hi> Head <hi>the other the</hi> Baſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Soule</hi> or <hi>Concaue</hi> ought indeed to be a perfect vniforme <hi>Cylinder,</hi> except in <hi>Chambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Cambered Taper</hi> and <hi>Belbored</hi> Peeces, but by reaſon of ill and careleſſe Foundings, few Peeces come to that perfection; neither doe ſcant any of their <hi>Soules</hi> lie exactly in the midſt of their Mettals, which (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for them the <hi>Diſpart</hi> and <hi>Diſpartline</hi> bee artefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and accordingly varied) cauſeth them to ſhoot awry, or ouer or vnder, or trauerſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The direct line, which by Mathematicall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, doth conioyne the Centers of the two Circles, is the perfect and true direction of all Shott made out of great Ordinance, I terme the</hi> Axis <hi>of that peeces</hi> Soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>Which may very properly bee ſo called, but it is vſually termed the <hi>Axis</hi> of her <hi>Bore,</hi> or the middle line of her <hi>Concaue Cylinder,</hi> thoſe two Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles at the extremes of that line doth with their planes make right and Orthogonall Angles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20147:5"/>
               <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>A marke is ſaid to lie within Poynt</hi> blanke, <hi>when the</hi> Peece <hi>being directed with her conuenient Bullet and Charge, is able to ſtrike and reach that marke.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>True it is, it hath improperly beene called <hi>point-blanke,</hi> as farre as any Peece conueyeth her Shott in a right line, neuertheleſſe the Peece bee mounted to the third or fourth point; But then if you aske how much that Peece ſhooteth at <hi>poynt-blanke,</hi> vnleſſe you alſo aſſigne the Mount, it cannot be certainely anſwered, And ſo conſequently there is no certaintie of that <hi>point-blanke</hi> for any Peece, becauſe then euery Peece may haue a thouſand ſuch ſeuerall <hi>Point-blanks.</hi> Wherefore I ſuppoſe it were more proper to call that only diſtance <hi>Poynt-blanke,</hi> which the Peece conueyeth her Shott in a right or inſenceable crooked line; the <hi>Axis</hi> of her Bore lying leuell with the <hi>Horizon,</hi> that is, ſhe being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mounted nor embaſed to any point, or minute of a point, aboue or vnder the Leuell, that being the only <hi>Blanke point,</hi> that is without numeration, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beginning, both of eleuation and depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. Diggs.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>A marke is ſaid to lie within the Mettall of the Peece, being dyrected not by the</hi> Axis of the Soule, <hi>but by the</hi> Coronice <hi>and vppermoſt ring of her Head, and Coyle, is able to reach the Marke.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
               <p>This is by <hi>Gunners</hi> termed ſhooting by the Mettall of the Peece, (or <hi>Mira Comune</hi>) whereby it is meant, that the Large line (which is that line which paſſeth vpon the vppermoſt of the Peeces Mettall, from the <hi>Breech</hi> to the <hi>Mouth,</hi> vertically ouer the <hi>Axis</hi> of the <hi>Soule</hi> of the Peece) bee directed to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20147:6"/>
marke, and is able to reach the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The difference of theſe two Ranges, I call the</hi> Difference of the leuell Range of the Soule and Body of the Peece.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>Which by Gunners is called the difference betweene the ſhooting a Peece by her due diſpart, and by the vppermoſt of her Mettall (or moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, the <hi>Baſe</hi> and <hi>Muzle</hi>-rings, at her Breech and mouth) and which (vpon the leuell) is neere about twice ſo much ground, as with a diſpart for her Range it is: But this holds not ſo aboue the leuell, in or neere double, for it only eleuates the peece a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fiue or ſixe degrees (in ſome peeces more, in ſome leſſe) to ſhoot by the Mettall more then by the diſpart increaſing vnder the mount of the beſt ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but leſſe being mounted aboue the ſame, ſo much as 4. or 5. or 6. deg. would encreaſe or decreaſe the Range for the Eleuations aſſigned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Axis of the</hi> Body <hi>of any Peece I terme that ſtraite line, which paſſeth between the Centers of the two outermoſt Circles at the Coyle and Head of the Peece, which in all</hi> Peeces, <hi>truly founded, is alſo the very ſame with the Axis of the</hi> Soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>Gunners and Gun-founders call the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ring at the Breech (the <hi>Cornooze</hi> or <hi>Baſe-ring</hi> of the Peece (which <hi>Mr. Diggs</hi> termes the outermoſt Circle at the <hi>Coyle,</hi> the other which hee calleth the outermoſt Circle at the <hi>Head,</hi> they terme the greateſt ring at the <hi>Mouth</hi> or the <hi>Muzle-ring:</hi> But that Axis cannot be the very ſame with the Axis of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caue Cylinder,</hi> in peeces that are not truly Founded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the two Axis differ, the Peece is falſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20147:6"/>
founded, and then they are either paralells, or make an Angle: if they be paralells, I terme it the Diſtance of the Axes of the</hi> Body <hi>and</hi> Soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>The definition thereof is very ſignificant and proper, for if in the Caſting or Founding of the Peece, the Axis of the Nowell that maketh the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Cylinder</hi> ſwarue paralelly aſide, it will make the Peece thicker of Mettall all along vpon one ſide, then it is vpon the oppoſite ſide thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If they be not paralell, their Angles of variation are conſidered two wayes; That is to ſay, in Altitude and Latitude; and thoſe Angles accordingly named the</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malie: <hi>Angles of Altitude or Latitude of thoſe Peeces.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe Angles of variation may be three wayes conſidered, that is, in <hi>Altitude</hi> only, in <hi>Latitude</hi> only, and in <hi>Both</hi> ioyntly, each of which will make the Peece ſhoote amiſſe, either ouer and aſide, vnder and aſide, or directly ouer or vnder the marke; and ſo for remedy thereof, the Peece muſt be differently diſparted, and accordingly alter her large line vpon the toppe of the Mettall, otherwiſe then it ſhould haue beene, if her Concaue <hi>Cylinder,</hi> had lyen direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly in the middle of her Mettall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt part of the violent courſe (of a ſhott throwne out of any peece of Ordinance) of Gunners ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> Poynt blanke reach, <hi>I call the direct line of the</hi> Bullets circuit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt vnderſtanding <hi>Gunners,</hi> leaue that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper phraſe or Name of <hi>Poynt-blanke,</hi> although it be very ancient (becauſe as I ſaid of the vncertainty therein, for there may be for one Peece 1000. ſeuerall <hi>poynt-blanks,</hi> if that diſtance which the Peece conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20147:7"/>
her ſhott in a ſtraite line, ſhould be <hi>Point-blank,</hi> it carrying ſo at euery ſeueral degree or point of moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, a ſeuerall diſtance; namely foure or fiue times ſo farre vpon the beſt Randon, as vpon the Leuell: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the leuell right Range, might moſt properly be called the <hi>poynt-blanke</hi> only, becauſe it is the Blanke point, and the beginning of Eleuation and depreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: each other point in either, hath its proper deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Numeration, as the firſt, ſecond, third, &amp;c. to the twelfth point, which laſtly is perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, either aboue or vnder the Horizon: And in place of Point-blanke therefore, they call that diſtance the ſtraite Line or right Range, proper for the mounting or imbaſing aſſigned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond part being a Curve</hi> Circuit, <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the foreſaid declination from the Axis, aſcending to the higheſt Altitude aboue the Horizon, and ending at a like Altitude to his beginning, I terme for distinction ſake his</hi> Middle Helicall <hi>or</hi> Conicall Arck.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>Gunners call it the <hi>Circuit</hi> of the <hi>Crooked range</hi> or Circular motion of the Shott, or the <hi>Mixt</hi> or Compound motion thereof; It perticipating of the violent, and the Naturall motions mixt together, beginning at the farther end of the ſtraite Line or <hi>Right Range,</hi> and ending at the firſt graze of the Shott, and being peculiarly differing in euery mount or <hi>Randon</hi> from all the reſt; And therefore in two or more ſeuerall Peeces, each like <hi>Randon</hi> in the one, is proportionall to the others like <hi>Randon:</hi> That is, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing both the Randons of one Peece, and one like Randon of another Peece giuen. The rule of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion will produce the Range for the other
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20147:7"/>
like <hi>Randon</hi> for the mounting ſought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The altitudes of any Bullets</hi> Circuit, <hi>I call that Line perpendicular, which by imagination Mathematicall, falleth from the Bullet, at his very higheſt of his Mount, perpendicularly downe to the plaine</hi> Horizontall: <hi>Which line of Altitude, coupled together with the right lines from the Top and Foote, Concurring at the</hi> Centre <hi>of the Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Circular Baſe, doth make a right angled Triangle.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
               <p>This and the two next Definitions, although they need no expoſitions, yet they haue good vſes in the Theorems following.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Horizontall line of that Triangle I call the Baſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maſter Diggs.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The other ſlope Line is the Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſall.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Peeces direct lyne of that Circuit which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes aboue the Hypothenuſall, (for deſtinction ſake) I call the Line</hi> Diagonall, <hi>For that there are ſeuerall of theſe</hi> Diagonall lines <hi>to all Angles of</hi> Randon, <hi>and together with the</hi> Horizantall line <hi>doe comprehend the Angle of the Mount.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>In my booke called the <hi>Art of Artillery,</hi> I terme that Hypothenuſall Line, the <hi>Secant Range</hi> of the Peece, becauſe the ſame properly repreſenteth as in the Doctrine of right lined <hi>Triangles</hi> the <hi>Secant</hi> of the Mount: As the aforeſaid perpendicular doth the <hi>Tangent,</hi> and the <hi>Horizontall</hi> the <hi>Radius</hi> thereof; which I ſo doe, the rather for the more eaſie and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Calculations therein requiſite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Peeces</hi> Horizontall leuell Range, <hi>I terme the diſtance betweene the Peece and the firſt graze of the Bullet, when the Peece vpon her diſcharge, lyeth leuell vpon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20147:8"/>
her Cariage, not mounted vpon any lofty plat-forme, but ſuch as lyeth, euen with the true Horizontall plane, wheron the Bullet muſt play.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>This is amongſt Gunners moſt vſually ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Leuell Range, which I call the Leuel-dead range, and ſo looke how farre the ſhott goeth direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (without any ſenſible declyning) is vſually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Leuell right range.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>All other</hi> Ranges <hi>made on any Horizontall plane, by the Bullet, when the Peece is mounted, at any ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> Randons, <hi>I terme the</hi> Horizontall Range.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>They are by Gunners called Randons or Ranges, and by me in the ſaid Booke, termed <hi>Dead-ranges.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And becauſe euery Peece hath ſome certaine grade, of the Quadrant whereunto mounted, ſhee maketh her vttermoſt Horizontall Range, in ſuch ſort, that if yee mount the Peece higher, the Bullet ſhall flie a ſhorter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and the Horizontall Range returne leſſe and leſſe againe: That point of the vttermoſt Randon Horizontall, I terme the</hi> Tropicke point or grade.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.N</speaker>
               <p>Which Range is called by Gunners the beſt of the Randon, and by mee the greateſt dead <hi>Range</hi> being the furtheſt diſtance that the ſame Peece can poſſibly conuey her ſhott: and that hath beene many yeares ſuppoſed to be at the mount of 45. degrees (as the meane or middle betweene the Leuell, and 90. degrees) But now it is found to be rather at the mean or middle degree betweene the Leuell and the degree of mounting, that in decreaſing, conueyeth the ſhott iuſt the diſtance of the Leuell Range, which is about 82. degrees, ſo that aboue 40. degrees aboue the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20147:8"/>
Horizon is the beſt of the Randon if accidents be excepted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that which ſerues for the diſcouery of the different violence of all Peeces right Lines or</hi> Right Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>howſoeuer Mounted, (By me called the lines</hi> Direct <hi>of the Bullets Circuit, and Lynes Diagonall, I call for deſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſake</hi> The Theoricke of Lynes Dyagonall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>For the <hi>Theorick,</hi> all Dyagonals (or more properly termed <hi>Right Ranges</hi>) for each ſeuerall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of mount of the Quadrant from 1. degree to 10. and ſo for each 10. degrees to 90. I haue thought good to adioyne an abreuiation of one of my Tables
<table>
                     <head>A Table of Right Ranges.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Gr.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>paces</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Gr.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>paces.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="10">
                           <hi>Leuell</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>524</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>209</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>695</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>227</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>855</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>244</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>930</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>261</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>1005</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>278</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>1140</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>285</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>1220</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>302</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>1300</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>320</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>1350</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>337</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>354</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
out of my Booke called the <hi>Arte of Artillery,</hi> (which hereafter I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to publiſh the vſe of the ſaid Table of <hi>Right Ranges,</hi> is thus,</p>
               <p>Firſt, if you know the right range of the Peece vpon the Leuell, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any degree mounted, you may thereby (with this Table) know vpon euery other degree of mounting the ſame Peece, how far ſhe will conuey her ſhott in a ſtraite Line, being like loaded, and hauing like accidents. As ſuppoſe for example, your Peece vpon the Leuell ſhoots 250. paces vpon the ſtraite Line; and you deſire to know how farre ſhe will ſhoote in a ſtraite Line being mounted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20147:9"/>
vnto 40. degrees aboue the Horizontall plane; ſay by the Rule of three: if 192. (the number of the Table for the Leuell) giue 250. your Peeces leuell right Range, what ſhall 855. (the number of this Table for 40. degrees) giue? and you ſhall finde 1113. <hi>(fere)</hi> the fourth proportionall, which is the Nomber of paces ſhe will conuey her ſhott, being ſo mounted to 40. degrees eleuation in the ſtraite Line or right Range ſought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The other that diſcouereth the varietie of Ranges of all Peeces, at all degrees of Randon, I call the</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke or Scale of Randons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>For the Theorick of <hi>Randons</hi> I haue alſo here epitomized another Table, out of my ſaid Booke of the <hi>Art of Artillery,</hi> whereby, for the ſixe firſt points of the Gunners Quadrant, you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the dead or Horizontall Range of one ſhott made out of any Peece, whether it be of the nature of a <hi>Culuering</hi> (which is betweene 30. and 40. Dya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitres of her Bore in length by the Range of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſet againſt the Letter S.) or whether it be of the quality of a <hi>Cannon</hi> (that is betweene 18. and 24 Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metres of her Bore in length, by the Ranke of Nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſet againſt the Letter C.) you may hauing one ſhott by the ſame, and the rule of Proportion, or rule of 3. knowe her dead or Horizantall Range for any other point of mounting ſought. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: ſuppoſe for a <hi>Culuering</hi> that ſhooteth leuell 260. paces: I would know how farre ſhe will conuey her ſhott vpon a Horizontall plane, ſhe being moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the third point (that is to 22. gr. 4.) Say as 192. (the number againſt S.) for the leuell range, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20147:9"/>
the Table giueth 2032. the number vnder the third point, what will 260. giue? worke by the Rule of three, and you ſhall finde 2752. for the number of paces that ſhe will conuey her ſhotte upon a Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontall plane being ſo mounted.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A Table of Dead or Horizontall ranges.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>points.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>S.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                        <cell>985</cell>
                        <cell>1623</cell>
                        <cell>2032</cell>
                        <cell>2185</cell>
                        <cell>2281</cell>
                        <cell>2300</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>paces.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>C.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>201</cell>
                        <cell>958</cell>
                        <cell>1600</cell>
                        <cell>1983</cell>
                        <cell>2135</cell>
                        <cell>2232</cell>
                        <cell>2250</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>paces.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The other Compoſed of All, and by Conference of all their parts together, framing a</hi> Theoricke <hi>of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, differing in all planes Horizontall, or varying for all kinde of Peeces, and Bullets whatſoeuer; Their Ranges and Randons: The Altitude of their Circuits, together with their Lines</hi> Diagonall <hi>and</hi> Hypothenuſall <hi>ſhall be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> The Theorick of Artillery generall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
               <p>I haue not here runne through all thoſe curious varieties, becauſe they require many experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, much Art, and large diſcourſe &amp; grounded vpon Mathematicall and practicall demonſtration: But, to know how much of the Horizontall Line, lyeth vnder the right Range or ſtraite Line of the ſhott (being found as before) for the Eleuation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, it is thus to be gotten: As the Radius is to the right ſyne of the Complement of the Eleuation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, So is the right Range to the Leuell diſtance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. And for the Leuell vnder the crooked Range, that is found by ſubſtracting the diſtance vnder the right Range, out of the whole diſtance of the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontall or dead Range ſound as aforeſaid, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20147:10"/>
remainder ſhall be the leuell Diſtance ſought. Laſtly, for the Circuits of the crooked Ranges, <hi>Mr. Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Tartaglia</hi> in the fourth, fifth, and ſixt Propoſitions of his ſecond Booke of his <hi>Sciencia Nova</hi> (which I purpoſe one day to Tranſlate, if God giue life, and no other man preuent me) doth demonſtrate, that the crooked Range of a ſhott made aboue the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, maketh more then a Quadrant, and vpon the Leuell a iuſt Quadrant, and vnder the Leuell, leſſe then a Quadrant. But for all his ſubtill Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it is not exactly ſo found by experience. For it is neither perfectly Circular elipſicall parabolicall, Hyperbolicall, nor Conicall, but meerely Helicall, or Heliſphericall, according to the proper Leuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, mounting, or imbaſing of the Peece aſſigned, which let now ſuffice.</p>
            </sp>
            <div type="theorems">
               <head>Mr. Digges his <hi>Theoremes, concerning the new Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of great <hi>Ordinance,</hi> reſoluing the moſt part of <hi>his</hi> Artillery Queſtions in <hi>Stratiaticos</hi> proponed.</head>
               <div n="1" type="theorem">
                  <head>The firſt Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>THere are three chiefe moſt materiall and effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſes of the greater violence of any ſhotte made out of great Ordinance, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Powder,</hi> the <hi>Peece,</hi> and the waight of the <hi>Bullet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="theorem">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20147:10"/>
                  <head>The <hi>2.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Powder</hi> is compounded of threee Principles or Elements, <hi>Saltpetre, Sulpher,</hi> and <hi>Cole,</hi> whereof <hi>Saltpeter</hi> is it that giues the chiefeſt violence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>3.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Albeit <hi>Saltpetre</hi> be indeed the onely or moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cauſe of the violence, And that Powder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly found moſt forcible, that is richeſt of <hi>Petre,</hi> yet is there a certaine proportion of Perfection of theſe three Components. And that in ſuch ſort, as if you adde more or leſſe Petre, the violence ſhall abate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Although Powder be alſo the moſt efficient cauſe of the force and violence of any ſhotte, yet is there ſuch a proportionall charge of Powder to be found for euery ſeuerall Peece, in regard of the proportion of her charged and vacant <hi>Cylinders,</hi> as giuing more or leſſe, then the ſame proportionall charges, it ſhall diminiſh, and not increaſe the violence of the ſhotte.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>If any two Bullets of equall quantitie, but vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall waight, be let fall from any loftie place to the Horizon, the more waightie ſhall euer fall the more ſwiftly: albeit not proportionally to their waight; which Axiome is indeed erronious, albeit a great Philoſopher hath auerred the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>6.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>If two equall Bullets of different waight, be ſhot out of one and the ſame Peece directly to the Zenith, both Bullets being of maſſie mettall, and charged with one quantity and kinde of Powder, the lighter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20147:11"/>
ſhall alwayes outflie the heauier. But ſuch kinde of Bullets they may be charged with all, as the Heauier ſhall outflie the Lighter, although they be both diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the ſame Peece, and quantitie of the ſame Powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>7.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>There is ſuch a conuenient waight to be found of the <hi>Bullet,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Powder</hi> and <hi>Peece,</hi> as the Bullets mettall being either heauier or lighter then that waight, ſhall rather hinder then further the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or farre range of the ſhot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>8.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>There is ſuch a conuenient Proportion to be found of the length of euery <hi>Peece</hi> to his <hi>Bore</hi> or Bullets Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amiter in reſpect of the <hi>Powder,</hi> and waight of the Ball, as either encreaſing or diminiſhing that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it ſhall abate alſo, and hinder the violence of the ſhotte.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>9.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>This proportion exactly found in any one <hi>Peece,</hi> doth not hold in all other, and yet the difference and alteration ſuch, as may bee reduced to Rules cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>10.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Beſides theſe three moſt materiall cauſes of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the Randons alſo and different Mounts of Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, cauſe a great alteration, not onely of the farre ſhooting of all Peeces, but alſo of their violent Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie. And albeit the different alterations are very intricate and ſtrange, yet haue they a <hi>Theoricke</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="theorem">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20147:11"/>
                  <head>The <hi>11.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>There are alſo many other Accidentall alterations happening by reaſon of the winde, the thickneſſe or thinneſſe of the Ayre, the heating or cooling of the Peece, the different manner of charging by Ramming faſt or looſe the Powder, by cloſe or looſe rouling or lying of the Bullet, by the vnequall recule of the Peece, either by reaſon of the vnequality of the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme or Wheeles, or by the vneuen lying of the Peece in his Carriage or deformitie of the Axtree, with diuers other ſuch like, whereof no rules cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine can be preſcribed, to reduce theſe vncertaine differences to any certaine proportions: but all theſe are by Practiſe, Diſcretion, and Iudgement to bee conſidered, and vniformely guided and performed in their beſt perfection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>12.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any Peece mounted 90. grades aboue the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, throweth his Bullet moſt violently immediatly after the diſcharge, and then the motion groweth ſlower, till the Bullet bee come to his vtmoſt Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and then by Perpendicular falling, encreaſeth by little and little, his ſwiftneſſe againe, euen till it come to the Horizon. But at all other Randons, it falleth not ſo out.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>13.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Albeit in the ſubtiltie of <hi>Geometricall</hi> Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no part of the Bullets violent motion, can bee truely auerred a right or direct line, ſaue onely the Perpendicular: yet in theſe experiments <hi>Mechanicall,</hi> That firſt part of the violent motion (I meane ſo farre as the Peece is ſaid to carry <hi>Point-Blanke</hi>) being ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20147:12"/>
neere the direct, is, and may well be termed the direct line. As all water leuels are accounted in all Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall operations, the Perfecteſt leuels and directeſt lines. Albeit the ſubtiltie of Geometricall Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, doth finde them not right or direct, but Curve or Circular.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>14.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>When any Peece is mounted directly to the Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith. Then doth his Motion violent (being in that ſcituation directly oppoſite to the naturall) carry the <hi>Bullet</hi> in a perfect right line, directly vpward, till the force of the violence be ſpent, and the Naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion haue gotten the victorie. And then doth the Naturall returne the <hi>Bullet</hi> downward againe, by the very ſame Perpendicular line. And ſo is the whole motion of the <hi>Bullet</hi> in this caſe a very direct Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular to the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>15.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>But if any Peece be diſcharged vpon any Angle of Randon, albeit the violent motion contend to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the <hi>Bullet</hi> directly by the line Diagonall; Yet the Perpendicular motion being not directly oppoſite, doth though vnſenſibly, euen from the beginning by little and little drawe it from that direct and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonall courſe. And as the violent doth decay, ſo doth the naturall encreaſe: and of theſe two right lined motions, is made that mixt Curve Helicall Circuit of the <hi>Bullet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>16.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any Peece therefore diſcharged at any Mount or Randon, firſt throweth forth her <hi>Bullet</hi> directly a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine diſtance, called of Gunners their <hi>Point-Blanke
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20147:12"/>
Range,</hi> and then it maketh a Curve declining Arke, and after finiſheth either in a direct line, or nigh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining towards it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>17.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The further that any Peece ſhooteth in her direct line, commonly called <hi>Point-Blanke,</hi> the deeper alſo ſhe pierceth in her Battery, if the Bullet bee not of ſubſtance brickle or frangeable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>18.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The more ponderous a <hi>Bullet</hi> is, the more it ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in Battery, albeit it pierce not alwayes ſo deepe as the lighter or letter ſhotte conueniently charged.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>19.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any two Peeces of Battery Ordinance, charged with one kinde of Bullet, and ſhott into one Rampire of maſſie vniforme kinde of Subſtance, ſhall euer make their Profundities of pearcing Proportionall to their leuell Ranges Horizontall, if they bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged either leuel or at one grade of Randon, and at like diſtance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>20.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any two Peeces of Batterie diſcharged into any Rampire of vniforme maſſie ſubſtance, ſhall euer make their Pearcing depths proportionall to their lines Diagonall, albeit theſe Peeces bee diſcharged from different Randons, ſo as they batter at like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>21.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>As <hi>Archimides</hi> line Helicall or Spirall, is made by the direct motion of a point carried in a right line, while that right line is Circularly turned as Semidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter vpon his Circles Center; So is this Artillery
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20147:13"/>
Helicall line of the Bullets Circuit created onely by two right lined motions becomming more or leſſe <hi>Curve</hi> according to the difference of their Angles, occaſioned by the ſeuerall Angles of Randon. Whereupon by demonſtration Geometricall, a <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oricke</hi> may be framed, that ſhall deliuer a true and perfect deſcription of thoſe <hi>Helicall</hi> lines at all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles made betweene the Horizon and the Peeces lines Diagonall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>22.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Theſe direct or Diagonall lines, are alwayes lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt when the Peeces Axis is directed to the Zenith. And alwayes as the Peeces Axis declineth more and more to the Horizon. So doe the Diagonall lines grow ſhorter, and at the leuell Horizontall, ſhorteſt of all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>23.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Theſe direct lines Diagonall, albeit they encreaſe in length at euery grade of Randon from the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon to the Zenith, yet is not their encreaſe vniforme or proportionall, either to their degrees of Randon or Horizontall Ranges, nor yet to their Circuits or Altitudes, and yet ſuch as may be reduced to a <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike</hi> certaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>24.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The middle <hi>Curve</hi> Arkes of the Bullets Circuits, compound of the violent and naturall motions of the Bullet, albeit they be indeed meere Helicall, yet haue they a very great reſemblance of the Arks Coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. And in Randons aboue 45. they do much reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Hyperbole, and in all vnder the <hi>Ellepſis:</hi> But exactly they neuer accord, being indeed <hi>Spirall</hi> mixt and <hi>Helicall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="theorem">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20147:13"/>
                  <head>The <hi>25.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any Peece diſcharged at any one Randon with like Bullets, and ſeuerall charges of Powder, ſhall make both their lines Diagonall and Curve Circuits of different longitude, but the Curve Arkes ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be as Paralels, and their Longitudes Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall to their lines Diagonall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>26.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The laſt declining line of the <hi>Bullets</hi> Circuit, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it it ſeemes to approach ſomewhat to the nature of a direct line againe, yet is it indeed ſtill <hi>Helicall</hi> and mixt, ſo long as there remaineth any part of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion violent. But after that is cleane ſpent, the reſt of his courſe to the Horizon is direct and Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and a perfect right line indeed, which is beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in thoſe Grades of Randon, which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Zenith and the Mount or Randon Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorizontall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>27.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>This declining line doth alwayes make a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and greater Angle with the Horizon, as you raiſe the Peece to a greater Mount, till you come to the Mount Equorizantall, about which Point the ſame declining line becommeth Perpendicular before the <hi>Bullet</hi> fall to the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>28.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The Horizontall Ranges in all Peeces mounted from the Horizon toward the Zenith, doth not ſtill encreaſe, but at euery grade of Randon are longer, till you come to the Point or mount <hi>Tropicall,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the vtmoſt Randon, which hath bin ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally thought to be the grade 45. but is not ſo. And
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20147:14"/>
from that <hi>Tropicall</hi> grade vpward, the Ranges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe againe till you come to the grade Aequorizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, ſo called becauſe the <hi>Bullet</hi> then falleth a like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the leuell Ranges.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>29.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>This Aequorizontall Grade is as far diſtant from the Zenith, as that Grade is from the Horizon, which ſhall cauſe the Peece to ſhoot in the Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall plaine a diſtance equall to his higheſt Altitude or longeſt line Diagonall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>30.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The Mounting of any Peece aboue his Aequori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontall grade doth ſtill decreaſe her Horizontall Ranges euen till it come to the Zenith. But in a Proportion different from any of the former, her <hi>Bullet</hi> ending euery of thoſe Circuits in a direct line Perpendicular.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>31.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The Gradual encreaſe and decreaſe of theſe Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Horizontall, albeit they are equall in the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, yet are they neither equall nor proportionall in the Horizon, neither the Ranges nor their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualls. Neither compared between themſelues, nor yet conferred with the Chords or Sines of their Arks. And yet is there ſuch a kinde of Proportionall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and decreaſe of the proportion of their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualls, as may be reduced to a <hi>Theorike</hi> certaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>32.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Tropicall</hi> grade commonly called the vtmoſt Randon, is not as hath beene generally ſuppoſed the Medium or Middle betweene the Horizon and the Zenith, <hi>Viz.</hi> 45. but rather betweene the Horizon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20147:14"/>
and the grade Aequorizontall, which will fall out much nigher 50. from the Zenith, and 40. from the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>33.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The higheſt <hi>Altitude</hi> of any <hi>Bullets</hi> Circuit is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt diſtant from the Peece, when ſhe is diſcharged at her vtmoſt Randon or point <hi>Tropicall,</hi> and at all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Randons either aboue or beneath that <hi>Tropicall Point:</hi> That higheſt <hi>Altitude</hi> is euer leaſt diſtant, and the baſes of theſe Triangles doe euer encreaſe to the Randon <hi>Tropicall,</hi> and decreaſe after, euen as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizontall Ranges; but in Proportion more different euery one from other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>34.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Altitudes</hi> of the Circuits of Randons doe not encreaſe and decreaſe as their Ranges <hi>Reciprocally,</hi> but from the Horizon in euery grade to the Zenith, doe ſtill encreaſe, but yet neither equally nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionally, neither conferred betweene themſelues, neither yet with ſines or Chordes of their Arkes of Randon. And yet the encreaſe and decreaſe of their Interualls Proportions, ſuch as may be reduced to a <hi>Theorike</hi> certaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>35.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Hypothenuſall</hi> lines of all theſe different Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits carry a mixt proportion of the compoſition of the Proportions of theſe <hi>Altitudes</hi> and baſes by addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Squares, But are not proportionall to the lines Diagonall of their correſponding Angles of Randon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>36.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any two Peeces of Ordinance being mounted to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20147:15"/>
any one Grade of Randon ſhall make their Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Ranges of their Bullets Proportionall to the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes</hi> of their Circuits.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>37.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The Ranges Horizontall of any two Peeces diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged at one Randon, will be alway proportionall to their lines Diagonall of the ſame Peeces Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>38.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The Horizontall leuell Ranges of any two Peeces of Artillery are euer proportionall to the vtmoſt Ranges Horizontall of the ſame Peeces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>39.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any two Peeces whatſoeuer diſcharged at one Randon, doe euer make their lines Diagonall, and lines of Altitude Proportianall howſoeuer the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions of their charges vary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>40.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any two Peeces whatſoeuer diſcharged at one grade of Randon vpon any enclining or declining Plaine ſhall neuertheleſſe make their Ranges propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall to their lines Diagonall and Altitudes of thoſe their different Ranges. Albeit the Peeces bee charged with a different kinde of proportion of Powder and Bullet, ſo as the ſhot be made in a faire Calme day, as is in theſe caſes alwayes preſuppoſed, becauſe for ſuch vncertaine Accidents there cannot certaine Rules Artificiall be preſcribed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>41.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>One Peece diſcharged at ſeuerall Randons vnder the vtmoſt Randon, being a like charged and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, and the Peece alſo of one temper, at both
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20147:15"/>
times, ſhall euer make ſeuerall Ranges. But if ſhe be diſcharged at ſeuerall Randons, the one aboue the <hi>Tropicke</hi> point, the other vnder, Then may their Ranges be equall notwithſtanding their Randons, <hi>Lines Diagonall, Altitudes, Baſes,</hi> and <hi>Lines Hypothenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall,</hi> be all different.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>42.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>When any Peece (being twice diſcharged at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Randons, the one aboue, the other beneath the <hi>Tropike</hi> point) ſhall make the ſame or equall Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in a <hi>Horizontall</hi> plaine. The middle grade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe ſeuerall Mounts is very nigh the grade of vtmoſt Randon: and the Peece Mounted to that middle grade, ſhall then make very nigh his vtmoſt <hi>Horizontall</hi> Range.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>43.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>The grade of vtmoſt Randon or point <hi>Tropicall</hi> of any Peece in a Plaine <hi>Horizontall,</hi> ſhall not be the <hi>Tropicall</hi> grade of that Peece, in a plaine declining or inclining, but an other Peculiar to that Angle of Inclination or Declination.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>44.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Any Peece diſcharged at his grade of vtmoſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage <hi>Horizontall</hi> vpon a Plaine inclining, ſhall not make ſo great a Range as on his plaine <hi>Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall:</hi> But contrariwiſe on a Plaine diſcending ſhall make a farther Range.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>45.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>A Peece diſcharged firſt at his due leuell, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at his Aequorizontall grade, albeit in the plaine <hi>Horizontall</hi> they make equall Ranges, yet in Plaines declining ſhall they not ſo doe, but alwaies the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20147:16"/>
Leuell Ranges ſhall euer out-ſhoot in all declining Plaines the Range of that grade Aequorizontall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>46.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>A Peece diſcharged at any grade from the Zenith to the grade Aequorizontall, ſhall alwaies make a greater Range in any Plaine enclining or declining, then on the Plaine <hi>Horizontall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>47.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>In all plaines enclining at all Randons betweene the <hi>Horizontall</hi> Leuell and point <hi>Tropicall,</hi> all Peeces ſhoote farther in their Plaines <hi>Horizontall,</hi> then on any Plaines enclining, and contrarywiſe in Plaines Declyning: But aboue the <hi>Tropike</hi> grade not alwayes ſo, but ſometimes, and not alwaies contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>48.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>In any Plaine whether it be enclining or decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if any Peece of Ordinance be diſcharged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Paralell</hi> or Equidiſtant to that plaine, and the firſt graze or bound noted. If the ſame Peece bee with like charge vniformely charged and diſcharged at ſuch an high grade of Randon as may cauſe the <hi>Bullet</hi> Range the former Diſtance: That middle grade of the Quadrant, which lyeth betweene theſe two Mounts, ſhall be very nigh the grade of vtmoſt adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, for that enclining or declining plaine. The which in all plaines enclining, will be aboue the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Range <hi>Horizontall,</hi> and in all declining vnder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>49.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>In all enclining or declining playnes, as the grade <hi>Tropike</hi> of greateſt aduantage doth varie; So doth alſo the proportions of their Ranges, at euery grade of Randon differ, whether they be accounted from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20147:16"/>
the Zenith, Horizon or Playnes, enclining or decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But yet in ſuch an aſſured and certaine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as may be reduced to a <hi>Theoricke</hi> perfect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>50.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>In all Grades of Randons, and in all manner of Peeces, whether the playnes be <hi>Horizontall</hi> or vary by Inclination or Declination, the <hi>Diagonall</hi> Lines are ſtill proportionall to thoſe of the plaines <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontall</hi> reſpectiuely taken by Graduation from the Zenith, in all Peeces whatſoeuer. But the Lines of <hi>Altitudes,</hi> their <hi>Baſes</hi> and Lines <hi>Hipothenuſall</hi> are euer different in euery ſeuerall Angle, both of Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and declination, and vary by ſuch a different Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion from the <hi>Horizontall,</hi> as they are to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by a ſeuerall Methode of Calculation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="theorem">
                  <head>The <hi>51.</hi> Theoreme.</head>
                  <p>Such <hi>Theorikes, Scales,</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> may be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the Inuention of theſe ſtrange Proportions of <hi>Altitudes, Lines Diagonall,</hi> and <hi>Ranges Horizontall,</hi> as thereby with the ayde of <hi>Calculations Arithmeticall,</hi> and ſome Rules <hi>Geometricall,</hi> a man may exactly and readily diſcouer the true Circuits and Ranges of the <hi>Bullets</hi> of all Peeces of Ordinance whatſoeuer, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted howſoeuer; and vpon all grounds or plaines en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining or declining, that can be Imagined, as ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the world by Gods grace ſhall bee made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="questions_and_answers">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20147:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr. Digges his</hi> Queſtions, in the Art of Artillery with <hi>Mr. Nortons</hi> Anſwers to them as followeth.</head>
               <div type="topic">
                  <head>Of Powder.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mr. Digge:.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHether there be not for any Peece proponed ſuch a certaine quantity of Powder to be found, as duly to the charge of the ſame Peece agreeth, And that in ſuch ſort, that charging the</hi> Peece <hi>with more or leſſe then that quantitie, it ſhall hinder the farre ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Bullet.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mr. N.</speaker>
                        <p>By the fourth <hi>Theoreme</hi> aforeſaid, There is ſuch a certaine proportionall charge of powder to be found for euery Peece, in regard of her Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and vacant <hi>Cylinder:</hi> But there muſt further be a conſideration had concerning waight of the Shott, the Fortification of the <hi>Peece,</hi> &amp; the different force of the ſorts of powder, each to be proportionall to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo three <hi>Dyametres</hi> of the Bore, or ⅓. of the waight of her Shott in Corne powder for <hi>Cannons.</hi> Or ⅔. of the <hi>Diametres,</hi> or ⅘. of the waight of the Iron Shot of Corned (Artillery) powder, for the <hi>Culuerings.</hi> And foure <hi>Dyametres,</hi> or the whole waight of the Shott of ſuch powder for Sakers, Falcons, and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Ordinance, is vſually accompted as their due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionall Charges, which charge (if it could bee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20147:17"/>
readily found) would be iuſt ſo much powder, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all fired within the <hi>Cylinder,</hi> will at that inſtant haue carryed the ſhotte iuſt to the mouth of the Peece.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether one and the ſelfe-ſame</hi> Peece <hi>twice charged with one and the ſelfeſame quantity of</hi> Powder <hi>and</hi> Bullet, <hi>diſcharged alſo at the ſame</hi> Randon, <hi>ſhall make the ſame Ranges?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for at the Second time it will ſhoote further then at the firſt: As well becauſe the Ayre that before was ſtill quiet and vnbroken, will be then moued that way the ſhotte goeth, and by the courſe of the ſhotte become broken. And alſo for that the charged <hi>Cylinder</hi> will then be dryer and warmer then at the firſt, and cauſe the <hi>Powder</hi> to fire quicker, and better together, which will adde more force there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If a Peece be diſcharged with the waight of his Bullet in</hi> Serpentine powder, <hi>and afterwards diſcharged with halfe the waight of his Bullet in ſuch</hi> Corne powder <hi>as ſhall cauſe the Peece to caſt the ſame ground;</hi>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>I demand if the ſame Peece be againe Charged with halfe the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of either ſort, whether theſe</hi> Ranges <hi>ſhall alſo bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall? The forme of Charging being vniforme, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Peece alike.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for the laſt halfes will one of them be then more farther off from due proportionall Charge of the ſaid Peece, then the other was from his Mate at the firſt; And therefore it is certaine, that the laſt halfe of the <hi>Corne Powder,</hi> will ſhoote
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20147:18"/>
much further then the halfe of the <hi>Sorpentine Powder</hi> can doe, becauſe there is more <hi>Petre</hi> in the quantity of the laſt halfe, then in ſo much of the firſt halfe of the <hi>Corne Powder,</hi> and leſſe in the other.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If two Peeces of the ſame Length and Bullet be charged with one kinde of</hi> Powder, <hi>but ſeuerall waights; I demand whether the</hi> Ranges <hi>ſhall be proportionall to the ſaid waights,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>Or to the</hi> Square, Cube, <hi>or</hi> Squared ſquare <hi>rootes of the ſaid waights: Or whether the Proportion of the</hi> Ranges, <hi>be not to be found, without any further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, either to the length of the</hi> Peece, <hi>or Ponderoſitie of the</hi> Bullet? <hi>Conſidering (by</hi> Hypotheſis) <hi>all thoſe are equall.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>Their <hi>Ranges</hi> will not bee proportionall to thoſe Roots, (beſides, whether they ſhould be alike or differently mounted, being not here expreſſed. Neither the different waights of the <hi>Powder</hi>) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without them, thoſe nor any other propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion certaine can hold; yet they may he found in a Compounded proportion, hauing reſpect vnto the proportions betweene the force of the Powder, waight of the Shott, and length of the Peece.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the Proportion found in one kinde of</hi> Powder,<note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>hold not in all other kindes, of what mixture ſoeuer it be, the</hi> Peeces <hi>and</hi> Bullets <hi>(being as is before ſuppoſed) equall?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for the proportions of all different kindes of <hi>Powder,</hi> equall in waight or Meaſure, doe differ in Force accordingly more or leſſe, as there is more or leſſe <hi>Petre,</hi> and working therein; Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20147:18"/>
the equality of the reſt, for that a leſſer waight or meaſure of ſtronger Powder will equall the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionall Force of a greater waight or meaſure of weaker <hi>Powder,</hi> and theſe are for Action in Geometricall proportion augmented, but for Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance they are augmented in Arithmeticall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as an excellent Philoſopher elſewhere doth largely Demonſtrate.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the proportion of ſuch</hi> Ranges,<note place="margin">He referreth this to a Booke neuer yet extant.</note> 
                           <hi>be not a</hi> Meane proportionall <hi>reſulting of the Commixion of the equality of the</hi> Peeces <hi>lengths and</hi> Bullets; <hi>and the inequality of the</hi> Powders <hi>Quantity? The Quallity being ſuppoſed alike.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſay it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſo neere to ſuch a mean pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionallity, as that in practiſe it might be accepted for the ſame indeed; But it not being exactly ſo, and alſo not being eaſily found, by reaſon it lurketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo many compounded varieties and contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we muſt content our ſelues with ſuch a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Neereneſſe, as in my Expoſition of <hi>M. Digges</hi> his Definitions are exemplified, or to be ſhewed elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where more largely.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="topic">
                  <head>Of the length of the <hi>Peece</hi> and <hi>Powder.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="7" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mr. Digges.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether two</hi> Peeces <hi>being in all reſpects equall, ſauing only in length, being charged with one</hi> Bullet,<note place="margin">Yes.</note> 
                           <hi>and one quantity of</hi> Powder <hi>ſhall not make equall</hi> Grazes?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20147:19"/>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for both by <hi>Maſter Digges</hi> his anſwer and mine to the firſt Queſtion, there is a Charge cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; which is, that two Peeces of ſeuerall lengths, and otherwiſe equall, cannot with one Quantity of like Powder, haue both of them ſuch a Charge, as can poſſibly be equally or proportionally neereſt to their Charge certaine; And therefore their ſeuerall <hi>Grazes</hi> muſt needs be alſo different.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Not alwaies.</note>
                           <hi>Whether the longer</hi> Cannon <hi>ſhall make the greater</hi> Range, <hi>whatſoeuer Quantity, or kinde of Powder they be diſcharged withall, the Quantity of</hi> Powder <hi>being equall?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>I imagine that <hi>Maſter Digges</hi> meant the <hi>Quality</hi> or <hi>Kinde of Powder,</hi> which may cauſe propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall difference, according to their ſeuerall Forces: Otherwiſe I may anſwer yes, vnleſſe the longer Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces charge be as much ouer, as the ſhorter is vnder, the Charges duely certaine.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>9.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Yes, but not without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Powder.</note>
                           <hi>Whether there be not a certaine conuenient Length of the</hi> Peece, <hi>in reſpect of his</hi> Bore <hi>or</hi> Bullet, <hi>to make the vtmoſt</hi> Range, <hi>in ſuch ſort, that making the</hi> Cannon <hi>lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſhall rather hinder then further.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Surely <hi>Maſter Digges</hi> meant herein as in the laſt, the length of the <hi>Cylinder</hi> or <hi>Chace,</hi> by name of making the <hi>Cannon</hi> longer, &amp; then the queſtion is by him truly anſwered yes. If the proportional Force and Quantity of the <hi>Powder</hi> be therein alſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and excepted; as I haue vnder his former Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions exemplified.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="question_and_answer">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20147:19"/>
                     <head>10.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether this Length and proportion being found in one</hi> Peece,<note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>hold in all other (the proportion I meane for the Length) muſt of neceſsity alter?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>One proportion cannot hold for <hi>Cannons</hi> and <hi>Minions</hi> of (not aboue 24. Dyametres) and alſo for <hi>Culverings</hi> and <hi>Sakers</hi> (not leſſe then 30. Dyame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres of their Bores in Length) and the greater waight of the greater Shott, reſiſting the powders Force ſo much the more, by how much the more the <hi>Peece</hi> is mounted, and doth likewiſe in his Courſe more (by the greater grauity thereof) affect to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend out of the ſtraite Line of her Courſe, then the lighter doth, though both beginning with equall ſwiftneſſe, each of theſe and all, or ſome of them together doe hinder generall proportions, beſides the leſſe proportion of fortefying of the <hi>Cannon,</hi> (which Mettall) then of the <hi>Culvering,</hi> and yet the proportion of the ſhott more increaſing in the Cube, cauſeth that the <hi>Cannon</hi> can neither burne within her, nor endure ⅘. in Corne powder of the waight of her ſhott, as the <hi>Culvering</hi> can doe, much leſſe as the Falcon, Saker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which can endure to burne within them, their ſhotts whole waight in ſuch powder, therefore they muſt needs conuey the ſhott a greater proportionall diſtance, then the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> or <hi>Minion</hi> can poſſibly doe, and conſequently breake the proportion aboue in his queſtion menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>11.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The proportion being by Experience found with</hi> Serpentine Powder <hi>according to the ordinary Charge;</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note>
                           <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20147:20"/>
                           <hi>Whether giuing like quantity of Corne Powder the ſame</hi> Proportion of Perfection <hi>ſhall hold,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> 
                           <hi>or a new bee ſought, in reſpect of the alteration of the Powder?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, that perfect proportion will bee alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and anew to be ſought, for there will a different quantity of <hi>Petre</hi> be found in the like quantity of thoſe ſeuerall powders; wherefore their Forces, and conſequently the <hi>Ranges</hi> muſt needs alſo differ. And further you may vnderſtand, that although <hi>Serpentyne powder</hi> be growne out of vſe (becauſe <hi>Corne powder</hi> is found better for Ordinance) and that the Force thereof was commonly accepted in compared pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to Corne <hi>Powder,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. to 1. Yet for that there is alſo in ſeuerall ſorts or Receipts of <hi>Corne powder</hi> greater differences of Force found betweene them: Therefore alſo the ſaid proportion cannot hold, for if in one pound of <hi>Corne powder</hi> of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of 6. 1. and 1. there bee 12. ounces of <hi>Petre,</hi> wheras in one pound of <hi>Powder</hi> of the receipt of 4. 1. and 1. there will be but 10. ounces and ⅔. of petre found; You may thereby alſo know what quantity of any one ſort or receipt of <hi>Powder</hi> will be of equall Force, with any aſſigned quantity of any other ſort of powder, whoſe receipt or mixture you already know, or can finde out, which you may eaſily doe many wayes; As in my Booke of the <hi>Art of Artillery</hi> at large is ſhewed.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>12.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If two</hi> Peeces <hi>being in all reſpects equall, ſaue only in Length, bee diſcharged with one</hi> Bullet, <hi>and Quantity of one ſort of</hi> Powder, <hi>make ſeuerall</hi> Ranges <hi>(at</hi> Poynt blanke <hi>diſcharged) I demaund whether the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20147:20"/>
ſame proportion of</hi> Ranges <hi>ſhall ſtill continue, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer Quantity or kinde of Powder the ſame</hi> Peeces <hi>bee Charged? The Quantity being alwayes equall,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumſtances in Charging and Diſcharging in either of them alike?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>The proportions cannot continue the ſame; For if in the former two ſhotts the aſſigned Charge be as much ouer for the ſhorteſt Peece, as it is vnder for the Longeſt, or in any other proportion, it cannot be in like proportion in the Latter two ſhotts.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>13.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If two Peeces in all reſpects alike, ſaue only in length, be charged with one Bullet, in</hi> Ordinary Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne-Powder; <hi>I demaund whether their Ranges ſhall beare the proportion of the length of their</hi> Cannons, <hi>or of the</hi> Vacant-hollow-Cannons, <hi>from the</hi> Charge <hi>to the</hi> Mouth? <hi>Or if it beare not the ſame proportion, whether they carry not the proportion of the</hi> Square, Cube,<note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>or</hi> Squared-ſquare Rootes? <hi>Conſidering all other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, all other things being equall ſauing only the</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons? <hi>it is apparant, that from their Proportion, as the Originall cauſe, the proportion of</hi> Ranges <hi>muſt in this caſe be deriued.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>We muſt conceiue that which <hi>Mr. Digges</hi> here and elſewhere termeth the Peeces <hi>Cannons,</hi> is the <hi>Vacant and Charged</hi> or <hi>Concaue Cylinder</hi> of the <hi>Peece,</hi> in her whole length within, or the <hi>Chaſe</hi> without. And to the firſt part of this double Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I Anſwer, that the aſſigned <hi>Charge</hi> muſt needs be neerer to her moſt due Charge certaine for one of the Peeces then for the other. And for the latter part
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20147:21"/>
I anſwer No, as vnto the fourth Queſtion: But to the Concluſion I anſwer, as I did to the firſt Queſtion, that from proportionallity of the quantity and force of the Charge, with the length of the Peece, and height and waight of the ſhott, the Proportion of Ranges for each ſeuerall Mounting is deriued.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>14.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If there bee three Peeces in all reſpects equall, ſauing in length of their</hi> Cannons <hi>or</hi> Cylinders, <hi>and yet thoſe three longitudes proportionall:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>I demaund whether the</hi> Ranges <hi>of their Bullets ſhall not be proportionall? All other Circumſtances ſaue only this of Lengths being one, equall, and alike.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>The longeſt will outrange the two ſhorter, if that Peece be ſo well fortefied, that ſhe can endure her due charge of powder, and ſo by the ſame reaſon the middlemoſt may outrange the ſhorteſt; And yet their lengths may ſhorten in ſuch ſort, that their Ranges vpon any like Mounting, or vpon the Leuell, may be proportionalls, but then the ſeuerall lengths of their Chaſes will not bee proportionall thereto: For that one, or thoſe two which are neereſt the due charge of Powder, ſhall carry the ſhott with more aduantage, then the more or moſt remote from their due charge, in regard of that which their lengths and waight of the ſhott can doe.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>15.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If three Peeces as afore, hauing the Longitude of their hollow or vacant</hi> Cylinders <hi>proportionall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> 
                           <hi>then (all the reſt being equall and vniforme,) the</hi> Ranges <hi>ſhall not be proportionalls?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20147:21"/>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſay no: If their Bore bee equall, their Charge equall, and yet their Lengthes ſhortening or lengthening by Proportion, becauſe the Charge will only in one of them come neereſt vnto the due charge, which aduantage will breake the proportion of it, with the other two; But if the middlemoſt for length were the neereſt vnto the certaine length due to the aſſigned charge of Powder, then the longeſt muſt needs be too long, and the ſhorteſt too ſhort, which diſaduantages would come neerer to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionallity, but not be exactly ſo; for diuers cauſes elſewhere herein ſhewed.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>16.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Or if in one of theſe Caſes the proportion of the</hi> Ranges <hi>be not a Meane Proportionall,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> 
                           <hi>reſulting of the commixion of the</hi> Equallity <hi>of the</hi> Bullets <hi>waights, the</hi> Equallity <hi>of the</hi> Powder, <hi>and the</hi> Inequality <hi>of the Longitudes of the</hi> Cylinders, <hi>either whole or vacant?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, it is doubtleſſe a meane reſulting pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionally of the Comixion of the equalities, with the inequallity, but alwaies with the former Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mentioned in the two laſt precedent Anſwers.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="topic">
                  <head>Of the <hi>Powder</hi> &amp; length of the <hi>Peece</hi> conſidered with the <hi>Bullet.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="17" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>17.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If a Peece twice charg d with one quantity of the ſame</hi> Powder, <hi>but the</hi> Bullets <hi>in waight different,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Note there is a meane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient.</note> 
                           <hi>I demaund whether the lighter ſhall alway outſly the heauier, or that ſome conuenient waight may be found?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20147:22"/>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>Doubtleſſe there is a meane conuenient waight may be found, which muſt be proportionall to the Force that moueth it; For a mans hand can throw a waight of 4. pound of Lead further then a waight of 20. pound of Iron, or then 2. pound of Feathers. And ſo ſhooting ſeuerally in a <hi>Saker</hi> three ſhotts, one of Lead, another of Iron, and the third of Stone with 12. pound of powder (as the Leaden ſhott would weigh) then will the Shotte of Lead outrange the other two, and that of Iron will out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range that of Stone; But ſeuerally ſhooting thoſe three with 8. pound of powder, as the Iron ſhotte weigheth: it will outrange the Lead ſhott, and the Lead the Stone ſhott: But ſhooting them againe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally with 4. pound of powder, then will the Stone ſhott outrange the Iron, and the Iron the Lead. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the more a Peece is mounted, the more doth the heauier waight of the ſhotte reſiſt the Mouer, which if it be too much or too little for the Force, it then impaireth the Motion; Therefore will the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meane waight be proportionall.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>18.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Yes.</note>
                           <hi>Whether this conuenient waight of the Bullet alter not, according to the Quantity or Validity of the Powder?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, for the Leaden ſhott will require the whole waight of ordinary powder, or ⅘. of the <hi>Corne-powder;</hi> And the Iron ſhott ⅘. of ordinary, or ⅔. of the beſt; And the ſtone ⅔. of the ordinary, or ½. of the beſt powder, As hath beene ordinarily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to doe generally his beſt execution; But this holds not alwaies for the force of powder and other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20147:22"/>
proportions and accidents are continually variable.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>19.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether to finde the ſaid conuenient Pondero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the Bullet, it be ſufficient to conſider the</hi> Powder,<note place="margin">Both.</note> 
                           <hi>or that the</hi> Longitude <hi>of the</hi> Peece <hi>alſo cauſe therein a diuerſitie?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, the longer Peece will require the more powder to be fired within her, before the ſhott can ariue to the iuſt mouth of the Peece to be then diſcharged out, then the ſhorter will, For if all the powder be fired before the ſhott ariue at the mouth, the after-running thereof within the reſt of the <hi>Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> will hinder the ſwiftneſſe thereof, by the <hi>Cylinders</hi> being too long. And likewiſe if the ſhott be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of the <hi>Peeces</hi> mouth before all the powder be fired, and that it haue receiued all the force of the Powder for want of ſufficient length in the <hi>Cylinder</hi> of the Peece, it will be alſo hindered. Therefore there is a conuenient length for the conuenient waight to accompany with it continually proportionall.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>20.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If two Peeces be twice charged, firſt with an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, then with a Lead ſhott; The Quantityes of</hi> Powder,<note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> 
                           <hi>at both times equall: Whether the differences of the</hi> Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>be not deriued only from the proportions of the</hi> Waights <hi>of theſe Bullets? (All other circumſtances by proportion differing not) And what relation to the</hi> Ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity <hi>of the</hi> Bullets <hi>theſe</hi> Ranges <hi>haue?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>To this I haue already ſufficiently Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, eſpecially in the three laſt precedent Anſwers, For as much as herein the proper waight of the Shot, &amp; due length of the <hi>Peece,</hi> proportionall to the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20147:23"/>
Force of the <hi>Powder</hi> and <hi>Heigth</hi> of the <hi>Bore,</hi> doe all domineere in altering their Shotts Ranges. And beſides we ſeldome vſe Leade ſhott, but often Stone ſhott in great Ordinance, wherefore the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and Anſwers may bee better applied to lion and ſtone, then to Iron and Lead.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>21.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note>
                           <hi>Two</hi> Peeces <hi>being in all reſpects equall, and charged with one kinde of</hi> Powder, <hi>but different</hi> Bullets, <hi>the one Iron, the other Lead; And either hauing the waight of his</hi> Bullet: <hi>I demaund whether the ranges be equall?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, but proportionall according as the length of the Peece is neereſt proportion as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>22.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note>
                           <hi>If one Peece bee charged three ſeuerall times, firſt with a Stone Bullet, then with</hi> Iron, <hi>and finally with Lead: And the</hi> Iron <hi>of ſuch temper, that it bee an exact meane proportionall in waight betweene the other two, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all diſcharged with one quantity of</hi> Powder, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund whether the</hi> Ranges <hi>ſhall bee in continuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for the length of the Peece; Height of the <hi>Bore,</hi> and force of the <hi>Powder;</hi> will be neerer the conuenient meane, for one of the ſaid ſhotts, then for any of the other two: Therefore the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued proportion will not hold herein.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>23.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note>
                           <hi>Whether a Peece being twice charged, firſt with</hi> Iron, <hi>then with</hi> Lead, <hi>hauing one quantity of</hi> Powder, <hi>and the</hi> Range noted; <hi>I demaund whether, being charged with any other quantity of Powder, the</hi> Ranges <hi>of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20147:23"/>
ſame</hi> Bullets, <hi>ſhall not alway retaine the ſame propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>I alſo deny that the <hi>Ranges</hi> ſhall retaine the ſame Proportion, for that the waight of one ſhott will neerer approach then the other towards the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient length of the <hi>Peece</hi> and force of the other quantity of <hi>Powder,</hi> And therefore that aduantage will alter the proportion therein.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>24.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If in a</hi> Falcon, <hi>for example,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> 
                           <hi>by experience I finde two ſuch quantities of</hi> Powder, <hi>as diſcharging the</hi> Falcon <hi>with the firſt Quantity of</hi> Powder, <hi>with an</hi> Iron, <hi>ſhott; and againe diſcharging her with the ſecond quantity and a Lead ſhott, they</hi> Range <hi>both duely one ground: I demaund whether in a</hi> Saker <hi>of the ſame Length with the</hi> Falcon, <hi>Charging her firſt with an</hi> Iron <hi>Bullet, then with a Lead</hi> Bullet, <hi>vſing the ſame quantities of</hi> Powder, <hi>whether their</hi> Ranges <hi>ſhall be proportionals? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubling either quantity of</hi> Powder, <hi>it ſhall alter the proportion of the</hi> Ranges?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N</speaker>
                        <p>I ſay vnto the firſt part of this double Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that the <hi>Saker</hi> ſhall not make proportionall <hi>Ranges</hi> of ground. Firſt, for that the <hi>Saker</hi> is of a higher Bore; And ſecondly, for that the conuenient proportions of Powder cannot agree with thoſe quantities (But I neuer heard of a <hi>Saker</hi> ſo ſhort as a <hi>Falcon</hi> by a foot at the leaſt.) And to the ſecond part I ſay, if at the firſt they had beene proportionalls, yet they would alter their <hi>Ranges</hi> by doubling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient proportions of either quantity of <hi>Powder.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>25</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If two</hi> Peeces <hi>of one Length be of ſuch different
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20147:24"/>
Quantity of</hi> Bullet,<note place="margin">No.</note> 
                           <hi>that the one being diſcharged with a</hi> Lead Bullet, <hi>the other with an Iron</hi> Bullet, <hi>either hauing</hi> Powder <hi>the waight of their</hi> Bullet, <hi>and ſo make equall</hi> Ranges: <hi>I demaund whether either of them diſcharged with halfe the waight of their Bullets in Powder ſhall</hi> Range <hi>alike alſo?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No certainely, for the halfes will bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of, (then the whole waights were) from the Conuenient meane: Therefore their <hi>Ranges</hi> will not be alike; for then the Iron ſhott will outrange the Leaden.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>26.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Not alwayes.</note>
                           <hi>If two Peeces be of one Length, but of ſeuerall quantity of</hi> Bullet, <hi>and yet of one kinde of Mettall or ſubſtance, and diſcharged with the waight of the</hi> Bullet, <hi>in one kinde of</hi> Powder: <hi>I demaund whether they ſhall not Range one ground, being equally Mounted?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Not at any time, if the Peece of the lower Bore haue her due length: For then ſhee will ouer-Range the other of the greater Bore.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>27.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note>
                           <hi>If there be once found by experience in ſome one Peece ſuch a perfection of a</hi> Cannon, <hi>as whether yee make him longer or ſhorter, hee ſhall Shoot leſſe ground, hauing alwaies the waight of his</hi> Bullet, <hi>of one kinde of</hi> Powder <hi>to his</hi> Charge: <hi>I demaund whether if another Peece whoſe</hi> Cannon <hi>or</hi> Hollow Cylinder <hi>is in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion like to the ſame, although greater in Quantity, ſhall not be of the ſame perfection?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, vnleſſe there bee a due conuenient Fortification and length of her <hi>Cylinder</hi> proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vnto the height of her Bore waight of her ſhott
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20147:24"/>
and Force of the Powder of her conuenient <hi>Charge.</hi> But with thoſe conditions I ſay, yes, it ſhall bee of like perfection.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>28.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If two Peeces hauing their</hi> Hollow Cylinders <hi>ſimiles or proportionall be diſcharged with the waight of their Bullets in Powder at like</hi> Randon,<note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> 
                           <hi>I demaund the proportion of their</hi> Ranges; <hi>the quantity of their</hi> Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>knowne?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>If the range of one ſhott be truly knowne of either peece, made (with like loadings and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents) either vpon the leuell or any Mount aſſigned, then by my Expoſitions before ſet downe vnder <hi>M. Digges</hi> his three laſt <hi>Definitions</hi> (preceding h s <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remes</hi>) both the ſaid <hi>Ranges</hi> may be found, as is well demonſtrated by <hi>Nicholas Tartaglia</hi> in his ſeauenth Propoſition of his ſecond Booke intituled his <hi>Noua Scientia.</hi> Where he ſaith, <hi>That euery Range or violent motion of a body equally heauy</hi> (as round ſhot is) <hi>bee it great or ſmall, equally mounted aboue the Horizon, or equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblique or paralell to the plane of the Horizon, they will make their Ranges like, and conſequently be proportionall in their diſtances.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>29.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of any two Peeces preſented, to know which ſhall ſhoot furtheſt, being both Charged with the waight of their Bullet in Powder, The force of the Powder being firſt in ſome one approued?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>If the Length of the <hi>Cylinders,</hi> bee in like proportions conuenient to their Bores Height and Charge, then the longer the Peece the farther ſhee ſhooteth. Otherwiſe the <hi>Cylinder</hi> (may by being too
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20147:25"/>
long) make the longeſt ſhoote ſhorteſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>30.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note>
                           <hi>Any two Peeces proponed, how to charge them with ſuch quantity of</hi> Powder <hi>as they may both at like</hi> Randons, Range like <hi>ground.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>There in the Force of the ſaid quantities of Powder, conpared with the length of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caue <hi>Cylinder,</hi> and waight of the Shott, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances muſt be conſidered: and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied that the Peece that would ſhoote fartheſt muſt be proportionally abated of her allowance of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as that which would ſhoote ſhorteſt is the more weake.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>31.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note>
                           <hi>Hauing proued any Peece at his vtmoſt</hi> Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>with any one kinde of</hi> Powder, <hi>to know how to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the</hi> Proportion <hi>of</hi> Powder <hi>from time to time in ſuch proportion, as the Peece keeping that</hi> Randon, <hi>ſhall ſhoote any part you will aſsigne?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Hauing by my anſwer to <hi>Maſter Digges</hi> his 11. Queſtion, or otherwiſe found how much <hi>Petre</hi> is in that quantity of powder proued, and deminiſhed it according to the force you deſire to leſſen; and hauing by my Expoſitions vpon <hi>M. Digges</hi> three laſt Definitions (preceding his <hi>Theoremes</hi>) found the <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> you may finde Leading markes: But proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall proofes manually acted, exceedeth Art herein, by reaſon of vnſeene accidents.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>32.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Not equall but proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall.</note>
                           <hi>Whether the right Line of the vtmoſt</hi> Randon <hi>be equall to the right Line of the</hi> Leuell Range, <hi>Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all Peeces they retaine proportion?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20147:25"/>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>The Leuell ſtraite Line or courſe of a ſhort explained in the 11. Definition contained in the 5. page, is at the beſt Randon, as 1. to 5. as <hi>Tartaglia</hi> and others haue demonſtrated agreeing neerely with experience; Therefore they cannot bee equalls, but they are alwayes proportionalls in all Peeces.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>33.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the right Line of the vtmoſt</hi> Range <hi>bee leſſe then the right Line of</hi> 90. <hi>Grades of</hi> Randon?<note place="margin">Yes.</note>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for the right Range or ſtraite Line of the Bullets courſe at the mounting of any Peece to 90. degrees, is there longeſt, and is directly perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular to the <hi>Horizon.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>34.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the right Line of the vtmoſt Range be a</hi> Meane-proportionall <hi>between the right line of the</hi> Leuell Range, <hi>and the right Line of the verticall</hi> Range,<note place="margin">Yes.</note> 
                           <hi>viz. mounted to</hi> 90. <hi>Grades?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, by the next anſwer following, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſtraite Line of any Peece, for each Mount is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionall to the ſtraite Line of any other Peece like loaded and mounted, compared with any Ranges of equall Mounts for thoſe Peeces giuen.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>35.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the right Line of the vtmoſt</hi> Randon,<note place="margin">Yes.</note> 
                           <hi>be not rather a meane proportionall, betweene the</hi> Leuell right Range, <hi>and that grade of</hi> Randon <hi>that</hi> Rangeth <hi>the ground of the</hi> Leuell Range?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, eſpecially in a Calme, and that meane proportionall will be found to bee ſomewhat aboue 40. degrees by the 19. <hi>Definition</hi> and the <hi>Expoſition</hi> thereof.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="question_and_answer">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20147:26"/>
                     <head>36.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Yes in a Calme.</note>
                           <hi>Whether the</hi> Right lines <hi>made by any two Peeces diſcharged, be not proportionall to the</hi> Ranges <hi>of their</hi> Bullets <hi>at the ſame</hi> Randon?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, by the 20. and 21. Definitions and Expoſitions hereof: And as it is well demonſtrated by <hi>Tartaglia</hi> in his <hi>Nova Scientia,</hi> and his <hi>Coloquies.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>37.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>
                           <hi>Whether the right Lines made by any two Peeces at any</hi> Randon, <hi>bee not proportionals with their vtmoſt</hi> Ranges?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes doubtleſſe, neuertheleſſe the 23. of <hi>M. Digges</hi> his ſaid <hi>Theoremes</hi> concerning great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance herein incerted; And as it will appeare by my two Explanations and Tables following his 20. and 21. Definitions aforeſaid.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>38.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note>
                           <hi>Whether the</hi> Vtmoſt Randon, <hi>(I meane to make the vtmoſt</hi> Range) <hi>be alwaies one, whether the ground bee leuell or aſcending?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, it cannot be ſo, for that the aſcending ground doth ſooner meet with the way of the ſhott, then the Leuell, and the Leuell ſooner then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending plane.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>39.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">No.</note>
                           <hi>Whether the Bullet end his</hi> Range <hi>with a Lyne, not ſencibly different from a ſtraite Line; As it doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin his Circuit?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, vnder 60. degrees of Mount, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 70. 80. and vnto 90. it endeth in a perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular right Line, which is a right and ſtraite Line.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="question_and_answer">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20147:26"/>
                     <head>40.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether all Peeces at one</hi> Randon <hi>diſcharged,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> 
                           <hi>as they make one Angle at the beginning of their courſe, doe make one Angle at the end of their Race?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, they doe as in <hi>Tartagliaes Nova Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> is demonſtrated, vpon all like planes, and meeting with like Accidents.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>41.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the Angle at the end of the</hi> Circuit <hi>made with the Bullet bee equall with the Angle of</hi> Randon?<note place="margin">No.</note>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, it doth not; for it is alwaies greater, except at the Mount of 90. degrees.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>42.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whether the vpper part of the</hi> Circuit <hi>made with the Bullet be a proportion of a</hi> Circle <hi>as</hi> Tartaglia <hi>ſuppoſeth?<note place="margin">No.</note>
                           </hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for it is a <hi>Mixt, Curved</hi> or <hi>Heliſphericall Line</hi> or <hi>Circuit,</hi> proper to the degree of mounting.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>43.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If a</hi> Falcon <hi>of three Inches Bullet waigh</hi> 700. <hi>pound, I demaund how much a</hi> Cannon <hi>of eight inches will waigh, that is able to receiue his proportionall Charge to that</hi> Cannon?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.N.</speaker>
                        <p>This cannot bee anſwered by the ſimple Rule of proportion, becauſe waight is not appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>Lines</hi> nor to <hi>Superficies,</hi> but vnto Solid Bodies. And alſo you may note that although <hi>M. Digges</hi> here compareth the <hi>Falcon</hi> which is at leaſt 30. of the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ametres of her Bore in Length, and Fortefied with Mettall to endure the waight of her ſhott in powder, with the <hi>Cannon</hi> that is but 18. or 24. Dyametres of her Bore in length, and no better fortefied then to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20147:27"/>
endure ⅔. of her ſhotts waight in Powder: But com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the <hi>Falcon</hi> with a <hi>Demi-Culvering</hi> that is of the ſame kinde and Fortification, whoſe ſhott waigheth 10. pound, the Queſtion is Anſwered thus: for</p>
                     </sp>
                     <div type="example">
                        <head>Example.</head>
                        <p>The Cube of three (the inches of the height of the Falcons Bore) is 27. &amp; the Cube of 4½. (the inches of the Demi-Culuerings Bore) is 91. <hi>(fere)</hi> Now ſay by the Rule of three,<note place="margin">Vnanſwered.</note> if 27. giue 91. what ſhall 700. giue? And ſo hauing accordingly Multiplyed the third number by the ſecond, and diuided the product by the firſt, you ſhall haue in the Quotient 2359. pound 7/27. for the waight of the ſaid <hi>Demi-Culvering</hi> ſought.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>44.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>If a Falcon of</hi> 3. <hi>inches Bullet require</hi> 3. <hi>pound of Powder for his charge, I demand how much Powder will charge a</hi> Cannon <hi>of</hi> 8. <hi>inches Bullet?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe this Queſtion is of ſeuerall kindes of Ordinance, as is ſaid in the laſt precedent Anſwer, I haue alſo applyed this Anſwer, and the <hi>Example</hi> to the ſaid Demi-Culuering thus: for</p>
                     </sp>
                     <div type="example">
                        <head>Example.</head>
                        <p>Multiply 91. the Cube of 4 1/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. by 3. <abbr>
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </abbr> the charge of the <hi>Falcon,</hi> and the product will be 273. which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide by 27. the Cube of 3. (the Diametre of the <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi>) And the Quotient I finde to be 10. pound and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. for the Powder of the due charge for the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Culuering ſought.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="question_and_answer">
                     <head>45.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>
                           <hi>If the</hi> Falcon <hi>that carryeth</hi> Point Blank 150. <hi>paces, and at the vtmoſt</hi> Randon 1300. <hi>paces: I demaund
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20147:27"/>
how farre a</hi> Culvering <hi>at his vtmoſt</hi> Randon <hi>will reach, that at</hi> Poynt-blanke, <hi>or Leuell rangeth</hi> 250. <hi>paces?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>Say by the Rule of 3 if 150. giue 1300. what ſhall 250. giue? anſwer, 2166. paces, and ⅔. for the vtmoſt range of the <hi>Culvering</hi> ſought.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. D.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And thus by obſeruations vſed in one Peece, by this Art of</hi> Proportion, <hi>a man may diſcouer the Force of all Peeces.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M. N.</speaker>
                        <p>The <hi>Gunner</hi> may know by her leuell right Range how farre his Peece will conuey her ſhotte at any Eleuation mounted: If he multiply the number of Paces ſhee carrieth in a ſtraite line, (ſhee lying le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell) by 11. and diuide the product by 50. the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient will be the greateſt digreſſion, which it maketh at the firſt degree more then at the Leuell. But all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degrees proceed alwaies deminiſhing vnto the vtmoſt Randon: and to know how they deminiſh, take the number of degrees from one to 41. the beſt of the Randon, and that will be 40. by which diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſaid number of the former Quotient; This Quotient will be the number of Paces, which ſhall decreaſe from degree to degree, from the firſt vnto the vtmoſt Random. As for <hi>Example:</hi> For the <hi>Culvering</hi> that ſhott 250. paces leuell in a ſtraite Line; I doe multiply that, by 11. and it produceth 2750. which I diuide by 50. and the Quotient will bee 50. paces; which it ſhooteth at the firſt degree more then at the leuell; which 50. paces, diuided againe by 40. (the degrees betweene the firſt degree and the vtmoſt <hi>Randon</hi>) &amp; this Quotient will be 1. pace and ¼. which I take from 350. namely from the 250. &amp; the 50. increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the firſt, and alſo the 50. to be increaſed for the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20147:28"/>
ſecond digreſſion, it leaueth 348. paces ¾ for the Range of the ſecond degree, vnto which adde 48. paces ¾. abating the one pace; ¼. and there will bee 195. ¼. for the paces of the Range of the third degree, and ſo proceed.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="errors">
               <head>Certaine Erronious Poſitions and Grounds publiſhed by profeſſors of this Art of Great Artillery, noted by <hi>Mr. Digges.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THat in all Peeces of Ordinance mounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the vtmoſt Randon, the Bullet is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently carried in a right Line to his vtmoſt diſtance from the Earth, and then falleth perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly downe to the Horizon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That all Peeces of one Bullet being charged with one quantity of the ſame Powder, and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at one <hi>Randon,</hi> ſhall make their <hi>Ranges</hi> proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall to the Length of their Peeces.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if you Charge any one Peece, with ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall quantities of one kinde of Powder (the Peece being diſcharged two ſeuerall times, at one Randon, and with the ſame Bullet, ſhall make different Ranges proportionall to the waight or quantity of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth and chiefe of all the reſt, is the Grade of vtmoſt <hi>Randon;</hi> For moſt Writers that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I read, agree in this, that the mount of 45. grades aboue the Horizontall plane, ſhould make there the vtmoſt Range.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That euery degree of <hi>Random</hi> doth equally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the <hi>Range</hi> in any one Peece, from the Zenith to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20147:28"/>
45. their <hi>Tropike</hi> grade, and ſo in decreaſing likewiſe, and that proportionally in all peeces more or leſſe according to their Force.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That in all ſorts of Peeces, the difference of their vtmoſt Ranges ſhould be in proportion anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the waight of their Bullets and Charges of <hi>Powder.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="errors">
               <head>Other Erronious Poſitions publiſhed concerning Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; Noted by <hi>Robert Norton.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THat when a Peece is to ſhoot at a marke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Leuell, being within diſtance of the right Range, then it by the vertue of the Fire that aſcendeth ouer-ſhooteth the Mark. And that therefore to remedy it, the Peece muſt bee ſo much imbaſed,<note place="margin">Sior. <hi>Collado. fol.</hi> 61.</note> vntill a Plum line at the Cornice let fall, will not enter but touch the lower ſide of the mouth of the Peece.</p>
               <p>The ſame Author there affirmeth Folio 60. that if any Peece be to ſhoote from aboue down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to a marke vnder the Leuell, and the Peeces Mettall directed to the marke, that then the Peece muſt be ſo much Eleuated more, as may equall the Angle, that the Peeces flatt of her mouth maketh with a Plum line applied thereunto to equall the Naturall defect cauſed by the ponderous deſcending of the ſhott in her mixt motion or crooked Range.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Smith</hi> hath publiſhed in his <hi>Art of Gunnery,</hi> page 35. that if a <hi>Saker</hi> will conuey her Bullet at <hi>Point blanke</hi> 200. paces, and at the beſt of the <hi>Randon</hi> 900. paces, that then that <hi>Cannon</hi> will ſhoote 1620.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20147:29"/>
paces at the beſt Randon that carryeth at <hi>Point-blanke</hi> 360. paces, which is very erronious, for that at the beſt of the <hi>Randon</hi> the ſhott rangeth rather 10. times as much as at the Leuell Range.</p>
               <p>And alſo page 39. he affirmeth, that if a <hi>Culvering</hi> be ſhotte off with 2/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. of the waight thereof, and then with the whole waight of her ſhott in Powder, that then the ſecond ſhott ſhall bee neere ⅓. further then the firſt.</p>
               <p>And page 46. that a Cannon that ſhooteth 1440. paces at 45. degrees, will for euery degree of leſſe Mount, abate 32. paces in her Range.</p>
               <p>And page 47. he ſaith that a <hi>Cannon</hi> that ſhooteth at her beſt Randon 1440. paces, will ſhoot at 30. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, but 960. paces, whereas in that caſe ſhee will conuey her ſhott being like loden and mounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 1269. paces.</p>
               <p>And page 49. he ſaith, that if you abate the Leuel Range of a Peece from the vtmoſt Range thereof, and diuide the remainder by 45. degrees, then the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient will ſhow you how farre the ſhott is carryed at euery degree.</p>
               <p>Or by deuiding the ſame number by ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, as you would eleuate your Peece at, The Quotient hee ſaith doth ſhew how farre the Bullet doth range beyood <hi>Poynt-blanke,</hi> and that thereby you may make a Table of Randons.</p>
               <p>But he either forgetting, or I thinke rather not knowing that the beſt Randon is but little aboue 40. degrees Eleuation, or that the Peece ſhooteth thereat about 10. times as much as the Leuell Range, Or that the Ranges deminiſh from 1. to the beſt Range, and increaſe from the beſt to 90. degrees Eleuation; It hath made him publiſh theſe and many other Erronious poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20147:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
